[Music]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee computer society by ieee software magazine online at computer.org software.
[Music]
save time building in-app chat voice and video for mobile and web apps using sendbird.
get to market faster with sembert's ui kit, pre-built ui components, best-in-class support and developer documentation.
join us in companies like reddit delivery hero yahoo sports and hinge.
start your free trial today at sunburn.com forward slash chat. hi.
this is priyanka raghwan for software engineering radio, and my guest today is jan iv dal who's the co-founder of the graph and project lead at edge and node.
janib has been working in crypto for more than three years.
and i had asked his team to send me a bio, and one of the things that really struck me from it was pretty interesting.
was his belief that decentralization will fundamentally transform how humans cooperate.
and he feels that this would only be possible if there's a fully decentralized protocol stack in place.
so we hope to cover all of this in the show along with the graph.
so um welcome to the show, yarner, it's a pleasure to have you on software engineering radio.
yeah, thank you so much for having me.
okay great, let's kick off.
we have done a few episodes on blockchain right, from episode 297 which was on blockchains.
and then smart contracts in episode 356, and then one on ethereum episode 343.
it's 2021 now, and our last episode was like three or four years back.
and we did you know smart contracts and ethereum.
and one of the things from that show was the host quoted the vision of ethereum, which was a one world computer with distributed nodes.
and making it programmable to build decentralized apps.
so i just want you to tell us about you know in this age.
i do know that we want to move away from what we have right now, which is our web which is controlled by these big technology companies.
and we want to move away from all of that.
so can you explain the relevance of blockchain infrastructure with this in mind?
absolutely, so you know it's been a really exciting time in the crypto space.
and you know glad to see uh you know renewed interest in the the software engineering field generally.
so yeah, you know there's really two big revolutions that are happening now within crypto.
one is the decentralized finance right, which is creating a decentralized money.
or you know large sets of you know currencies and different contracts and ways of you know programming money and finance.
and the second is this web three space, which is you know decentralizing information systems as a whole.
and the problem that you know we're solving is that you know all software today basically is you know run owned and controlled.
by whatever company it is that's providing the software.
and it's very easy to just assume that that is you know how it always was and that's how it always will be.
but you know the history of software is you know really quite rich with changes in paradigms and computing.
you know starting with you know mainframe computers where you know you only had large corporations that were running these mainframes.
to you know the personal computer where you know people were getting their software primarily through you know cd-roms or floppy disks.
where they could run that software you know locally on their computers.
and then now to the web, you know which has made things a lot more convenient.
because you know you don't have to acquire software like physically through the mail or in a store.
you know you have teams of software developers that can just you know issue upgrades.
and it makes you know coordinating a lot easier.
but you know there's this really massive thing that you know we're giving up, which is we give complete control over to the companies that are running that software.
and what we've seen over the last 20 years is that really creates an extraordinary centralization and concentration of power.
where there's fewer and fewer companies making more and more decisions around how you know everybody can live their lives run their businesses.
and you know it's really not great for an open free society.
and so with web3 we're rebuilding the protocol stack.
so that you can still have these same kinds of great you know internet connected applications.
but where users you know have a new set of guarantees.
and there's no you know company or even set of companies that have you know control over how the software is run.
and instead you have individuals with a lot more control over for example you know their private data, their reputations.
the things that you know they're contributing that's theirs.
and you can also have more open governance processes.
so that where there's you know many participants that are all you know working together in some way.
uh the rules for you know how those participants work together is open and transparent.
and can be upgraded through you know transparent governance processes.
so you know that's what we're working on with web three.
and a ton of progress has been made over the last few years.
okay, janab, i actually have to ask you a sort of a non-technology question right now.
and the reason i'm asking is i live in india, and just last week we have a big press item.
that was uh the government is planning to ban bitcoins as well as you know other virtual currencies.
and they want to have you know some oversight on this.
i think of it as like there's some sort of trust deficit that they have.
and without going into too many details of that i wanted to ask you, you know there are certain countries.
and maybe you know other organizations which have a problem with the blockchain infrastructure.
what's your take on that, it was just curious to know before we jump into the you know the technology?
yeah absolutely, i mean you know it's not every day that you know the global monetary system you know sees a change.
and certainly you know large countries, and i mean all countries you know part of their job is to try to create stability.
they also have in a certain amount of like sovereign control that they expressed through their monetary policy.
and you know for the last you know 100 plus years you know there's basically been this link between state and money.
the same way that in the past you know between the state and say religion.
where you know if you lived in a certain country you know the king and the monarch decided like everyone in this country must you know adhere to this religion.
and then you know famously you know in the united states and you know many other countries.
and now you know most there's a separation there, you're free to choose your own religion.
and i think a similar thing is happening now with money.
where it's been in the providence of countries, it's given a lot of power to politicians to you know banks.
to you know the large established financial you know players, and now there's going to be some competition.
and so you know different countries are grappling with fact in different ways.
i think you know the world is a lot more global now, and so there's you know a lot more possibility for like international competition in these types of areas.
and ultimately i think the countries that embrace this new technology are just going to be the most competitive ones.
and i think you know in the early stages of these types of new technologies you know it's not as obvious what all of the benefits are.
because these things they really accrue as the technology grows.
but i think you know with crypto for example we're already getting to a place both with decentralized finance and with web 3.
where the benefits are you know just becoming more and more clear every day.
and so it's gonna you know rapidly get to a point where it's just too hard to ignore.
and i think then the policymakers just have to figure out how to deal with that reality.
great great answer, so let's just move on to the meat of the show.
i want to talk about the blockchain infrastructure referencing your talk from this thing that you do at your the draft day.
there was a talk from two years back, i think you talked about you know web 3 and web 2 and the difference is like what you've just detailed.
but you said that certain aspects of web 3 was still not at the level of web 2.
you talked about you know infrastructure in terms of scalability, performance being not that great in the ux also not being so good.
it's been now two years since that talk, so what's your take has how are things measuring up now?
i think we've made a ton of improvements over the last two years.
um so i can go through some of the places where i think things are looking really good.
but definitely the web3 platform is still a platform that you know is under construction now.
you're seeing some really great applications already coming out on top of this platform.
so i think you know that's really exciting.
you no longer have to just dream to kind of think about how these decentralized applications might work in the future.
they're actually you know already quite a few that are live, and so you can see it. but we still have a long way to go.
so as far as the infrastructure you know web3 is composed of you know maybe a dozen to two dozen let's say different protocols, different layers in the stack.
so you've got you know block chains are an important part.
because they give you this global consensus where you can have you know people all over the world.
that can agree at any given point in time on the state of a shared database.
so that's a really important primitive.
you've got layer two solutions that are built on top of blockchains that allow them to scale.
because you know the base layer chains themselves have to optimize for security.
you know because anybody can run these nodes, they need to be secure.
and you know that's inherently you know puts a limit to how fast you can process transactions.
and so with layer twos you can you know get a big speed up in the number of transactions that you can process per second.
that's an important part of the stack.
you've got peer-to-peer protocols, so not everything needs to go directly on a chain.
if you're doing some work using an application locally that data should really never leave your device.
you should be able to work in this kind of offline first way.
and you know that way your private data really remains private.
and then if you need to collaborate with some other people that data should really just be exchanged directly peer-to-peer.
there's just no reason to go through these kind of centralized you know intermediaries and services.
that in you know have to inspect and relay all of your data just to be able to collaborate you know with the co-worker.
so there's you know these sets of peer-to-peer protocols that enable that.
we've got things like wallets which is how people interact with these protocols.
where you can store your crypto and you can kind of pay for the different services that you're consuming.
and you know of course the graph for indexing all of this data and making it easily accessible.
and actually serving the data to the applications.
so these are just a few of the different types of protocols, and there are even more.
and we've really seen a lot of progress you know in the last two years.
so um ethereum for example is they launched the phase zero, they call it uh their eth2.
which is just a massive upgrade to the ethereum blockchain.
we're seeing a host of layer 2 solutions, several of which have already been live for some number of months.
and several of which are launching in march you know this month and coming up.
so you know it's just a really dynamic time with you know new protocols launching you know every week.
and these protocols that are launching have really been under development over the last two years.
and so this period right now is one of really rapid innovation.
a lot of you know new protocols coming to market with you know res you know deep research and engineering behind them.
and i think this is the year that we then have to stitch together these different protocols into a really cohesive platform.
and make it really easy for developers to build these decentralized applications on top.
and so i see 2021 as being you know the big year for web3 infrastructure.
and you know we're already seeing the first you know amazing applications you know being built on top.
and uh you know we expect that to accelerate.
okay, so let's get into the graph.
you explained it briefly, but could you just reiterate to our listeners what's the problem that you're solving?
and a lot of articles i've read online has called you the google of blockchains, do you like that?
sure yeah, i mean i think it makes sense because you know google basically you know indexes the web.
and the graph is you know indexing blockchains and all these decentralized networks.
so yeah, the problem that we solve is if you want to build a decentralized application on top of these networks.
before the graph it was really hard because you know these nodes don't store all of the data in a format that you can consume directly.
and so you know when we started building on top of ethereum in 2017 we realized you actually can't.
you know you couldn't at that time build decentralized applications.
you would have to actually run a custom proprietary server to index that data and serve that data to your application.
and you know whenever you have these centralized points of failure you know that tends to be where things get like corrupted.
where you know power struggles ensue because you know everyone wants to control the things that are controllable.
so we invented the graph which is you know an indexing protocol.
where developers can build and specify these sub graphs which are open apis that anybody can query.
it uses graphql which is a really popular query language originally from facebook, and it's been open source.
and it's used by a lot of the top you know web and mobile companies.
and so with these sub graphs you have really easy convenient access to all of this data.
but that data isn't running on proprietary servers, instead it's running on a decentralized network.
so you can publish these subgraphs to the network, and these indexers are the node operators that participate in this network.
and they run you know these subgraphs where they're ingesting the data from the underlying networks.
processing them according to these like etl rules that you give them, they index that data.
and then they serve it efficiently to clients.
and there's a whole economic system here that uh you know creates the right types of incentives for these node operators and for other participants in the network.
and the goal of the system is really to index all of the world's public information.
you know allow curators to organize that data in a decentralized way.
and then you know be kind of the backbone in serving all of these uh decentralized applications.
okay, so if i were to understand that a little bit like could you like uh run us through a case study?
i looked at your blog and there's you have something called the query market.
so if i was a consumer and i wanted to i'm looking i'm at the query market and i'm looking for a particular query.
what's the sequence of events i would do with the graph?
sure yeah, so as a developer you know let's say you want to build a decentralized application that allows people to you know find and purchase nfts right.
nft or this uh really exciting you know thing happening in in the crypto world right now.
where people can mint and buy and sell provably rare goods.
and one of the areas where this is getting really popular is with art.
where you can be an artist and you can now like issue your art digitally.
and you can have you know for example just a single edition of this piece of art.
and you can put it up for auction, people can bid on it.
and then they you know will own you know your you know one of one edition piece of art.
so it's you know really cool area that's been really kind of blowing up.
and it's it's bringing a lot of uh now like resources to artists which is awesome.
so if you want to build that kind of an application you would go to the graph.
and there's an explorer where you can browse all of the different sub graphs.
and you can find subgraphs from you know the top nft projects like zora and foundation super air known origin.
and those sub graphs have these graphql you know schemas.
and so graphql is this really convenient query language where you don't really have to like know too many details about what's happening under the hood.
you just kind of ask for the data that you want, it's a very intuitive kind of language.
and you can you know run a query and get that data you know directly back.
and so then you have basically this open api endpoint that you can just plug into your front-end application.
you know where you can like query for you know all of the nfts that are available for auction.
you know sorted by price or however you want to like you know query that data.
and you can just you know drive your user interface directly from that api.
so that's kind of how it works from a developer's perspective.
and then they are paying query fees into the network you know as people use the applications.
now we're still kind of in this process of migrating these daps to the decentralized network.
so we launched the network in december, and in the first quarter of this year the big focus was around bootstrapping the supply side.
getting all the indexers on the network.
there are some other roles and things that you know we're focusing on kind of building up that supply.
and just yesterday we announced the migration plan for bringing sub-graphs that previously were running on a hosted service.
that we we initially been writing just kind of you know for development you know while we were working on the decentralized network.
and we're going to be migrating those sub graphs to the decentralized network.
and so that's when we're going to see all of the like micro payments and these kinds of things going into effect for the decentralized network.
and so i can share a little bit more details about how that works if you're interested in going into them. yeah probably actually there's one more thing i wanted to ask you.
you did throw like you know the different players in the architecture of the graph.
i think you you had used the term curators could you maybe like tell us the different roles which are there?
absolutely, so indexers i mentioned are the node operators that they're running the servers.
you can think of them as like the distributed devops team right.
there you're like database administrators that you know you just don't have to think about running servers and databases anymore.
you just outsource it all to these indexers.
then the curators are the ones that are organizing all of the data on the graph.
so they may be the subgraph developers themselves that are building these subgraphs.
or they can just be you know anyone who goes through and evaluates the quality of subgraphs.
you know because anybody can build these subgraphs, it's a permissionless network.
you know you want people whose job it is to evaluate them and figure out which ones are you know pulling in accurate data.
doing the calculations correctly are generally useful.
and so that's the role that the curators play in the network.
and then you've got delegators who are the ones they help secure the network by staking tokens on indexers.
so with a lot of these decentralized networks they use staking as a way of enforcing security in the network.
and so you know it's an open permissionless network anyone can participate.
but then how do you know that they don't misbehave, so with staking somebody is locking up tokens basically.
as you know it's like a bond where if the service provider misbehaves then they can be slashed.
which means that they lose those tokens are taken away.
and so that creates the incentive for them to behave according to the rules of the protocol.
and so delegators stake their tokens on indexers, and that helps provide this additional.
you know they call it civil resistance, but it's kind of you think of it as security in the network.
and then you've got consumers uh which are the ones that are actually issuing the queries and paying for the queries.
uh using these micro payments.
so you know this was an idea that you know existed early on in the web, and it never got implemented.
but this idea that you could stream these micro payments for these api calls.
and now you know for the first time we can actually do that.
and so that's the model in the graph where you pay per query.
now long term our vision for web 3 is that users are going to pay for the metered usage of the services that they consume.
so you know you'll have a wallet on your phone on your your desktop.
and you know you're just kind of streaming for these for the metered usage of these different applications.
and then in that world the developers don't actually have to pay for the infrastructure.
and that's actually a really important change that enables this kind of you know pulling away the reliance on these centralized service providers.
because that's kind of the deal that we're in with these large centralized internet companies.
is because they're running the infrastructure and because they're the ones paying for it.
we basically have to you know play by their rules.
and if we want to you know kind of get our freedom back then you kind of have to ship the model of who's paying for it.
and so this way it's not a single company that is like running the application, but rather right it's these decentralized networks.
and then it's the consumers that's paying.
and and you know at the end of the day the cost for the software you know is not that high.
you know the the amount of database or compute cycles in any you know individual uses is fairly marginal.
and so it's actually you know better to be able to just kind of pay directly for the stuff.
then um you know to really kind of get trapped and monetized through you know ways that you you can't control.
so so that's kind of the long-term you know vision for web3.
but in the short term because you know there's kind of a an education component here. and some of the tooling still kind of needs to be improved.
it's basically the dap developers right, the decentralized application developers that are going to be paying for these queries in the network.
and so there for the time being it those are the consumers.
and so that's the different roles in the network.
interesting quite a lot of uh different concepts there.
so you're saying uh currently as a as when i go to cloud service provider i have this as a service model right.
now is my understanding correct that you would be having that kind of a model?
or well in a sense where you know you're only paying for what you use right.
so i guess since there it's most similar to you know one of these serverless sort of like function as a service style.
um you know cloud offerings where you're paying per query.
but the difference is that you know with with the cloud provider first of all it's a single company you know say amazon that's running those servers.
whereas in you know this decentralized network it's uh you know there's a large number of service providers that are competing.
and you know in the cloud model that that cloud provider is the one like setting the prices.
and you know with these decentralized networks it's an open marketplace.
and so all of these different service providers are competing to provide the best service at the lowest price.
and so how you design these markets is really like a core part of the protocol design.
and you do it in such a way that it creates the right incentives for for people to really you know compete.
and and be able to provide better services.
okay the next thing i want to ask you is a little bit on also the when you return a query from the graph.
i don't know if this is a dumb question to ask, but what's the guarantee that the response is correct?
is that guaranteed by the roles that you just explained or?
yeah so the way the b1 you know graph protocol v1 enforces security is every query that you issue.
the indexer returns the response along with an attestation.
so it's assigned attestation that then the client can use to issue a dispute.
if you know they think that the data is incorrect.
and so there's this whole kind of like dispute resolution protocol where there's an arbitrator that can come in and adjudicate the dispute.
and if the dispute is found to be correct then the indexer loses their deposit their stake.
and so this is where you know the amount of stake that an indexer you know has put down in the network.
basically tells you how much security there is there because you know they can lose that much money.
so for example right now in the decentralized network they're about 170 indexers.
many of them have have staked you know millions of dollars each in the network.
which means if they send you back an incorrect query response you know they're on the hook for for millions of dollars in that event.
and so that's what creates kind of the checks and balances for the indexers to behave correctly.
so that's a lot that we've covered right now with the graph at a high level.
so let's move on to a little bit about you know as a developer if i wanted to come onto the graph network.
and i want to write some code is there a playground to familiarize oneself?
yeah if you go to thegraph.com you know we've got really great docs there that can help you get you know up and running really quickly.
and then there's an explorer which is where you can browse and discover all the different subgraphs that different developers have built.
and you can see the graphql playground there where you can just kind of run example queries in the browser.
and you know really explore the raw data itself that's being indexed on the graph.
so it's really easy to get started both as a dapp developer.
you know if you want to build basically user interfaces you know different applications that just consume all of this data from the graph.
or you can also get started as a subgraph developer and actually build these apis.
and the subgraph developers are you know it's a really kind of interesting role.
because you're basically you know getting in depth you know understanding the details of all these different protocols.
and then abstracting the complexity away that's what these sub graphs do.
so you know there are a lot of for example d5 protocols being built on ethereum.
where you know actually going through the smart contracts understanding what they're doing is fairly involved.
and as a subgraph developer you know you can ingest all of that data and put it in a really convenient format.
that then gives the dapp developers a much easier interface for interacting with these systems.
so it's kind of cool to you know have this sort of specialization.
you know between the subgraph developers with details of the underlying protocols.
the dap developers then you know really don't have to be super technical.
you know you can be more of like you know a designer or a you know just a product you know engineer.
and easily you know access like the sum total of this you know giant global api that is just made available for you.
i wanted to ask you about this how do you run these draft nodes.
like i do see some things on the literature in your blog.
is for example on having two kinds of ways in which you could have a node.
you could either be have your own infrastructure running this node, or you could have a hosted service.
can you explain that a little bit to our listeners?
yeah so you know the graph is a decentralized protocol, everything is open source.
so the main kind of code base is called graph node.
that's the software that does all of this like etl work, indexes the data, you know serves the the graphql apis.
it's written in rust, and if you want to you know run a graph node yourself uh it's it's pretty easy to do so.
then in early 2019 the initial team you know launched a hosted service.
where you know we're running a bunch of these graph nodes so developers could easily get started building on the graph.
you know that host of service has been running now for about two years, and it's been growing tremendously in usage.
and then the decentralized network launch into december.
and as we kind of announced we're going to be you know migrating subgraphs over from the hosted service to the decentralized network.
so going forward you know the main kind of pattern for most developers.
we expect that they would use some kind of something that looks and feels like the hosted service.
maybe in development we're going to be uh announcing some new products you know in that area.
that still makes it like a good development environment.
and then once a subgraph is you know been tested you've gone through your own internal qa process.
then you'll be able to just publish it to the decentralized network.
and that's where it runs long term.
and you know the beauty of publishing to the decentralized network is that you know nobody needs to trust that.
like some particular team is going to continue to operate those servers correctly.
right it's you basically you know are guaranteed at that point that that api will be available as specified.
for as long as anybody wants to use it.
um and that's a really cool kind of guarantee that has never really existed before in software.
you know i i can't tell you the number of either you know services that i've used or applications that have either you know uh gotten shut down.
or the team got acquired or you know for you know whatever reasons they change product directions.
and you know it's you know this awful part of depending on software that other people run.
and so you know by actually building software on top of these decentralized networks.
you know we're building these like stable building blocks.
where you know it's pretty incredible to just think like this thing if if someone wants it a hundred years from now.
it'll be here a hundred years from now and continue to run exactly as specified.
so what about updates that you do, how does i have little trouble wrapping my head around that?
so the updates to like a new like when you have when you publish something you say it's there forever.
so i have like you know coming from this web 2 world i have like a little trouble understanding that's like.
what about like if you want to make some changes to something?
yeah absolutely, and of course you know we're software developers things change.
and so you know the mental model here is is similar to that of like immutable data structures.
so you know if you're familiar with you know functional programming principles.
you know with immutable data structures you accrete changes over time.
but the underlying you know data itself isn't modified.
so you kind of have pointers to these data structures that grow and evolve over time.
and so it's kind of similar with you know how we kind of construct uh things in web three.
where for example you've got the blockchain right, the history of data on a blockchain never changes.
but new blocks get added you know every few seconds.
um and so it's this kind of like immutable growing data structure.
similarly um there's a you could think of it as a protocol, but it's it's called ipfs or the interplanetary file system.
that gives you content address storage which is a really brilliant idea.
you know instead of referring to a server url you know google.com you know my file.
which at any point in time could change and and you'd have no idea you know if and why and when.
you know the response that that url is going to change.
with ipfs all content is content addressed, and so you build up a hash of the file itself.
and so you have this you know this this hash and that uniquely identifies the file.
and if you want to get it from a particular server you can.
or you can you know you know get the file in a peer-to-peer decentralized network.
and you can calculate once you've gotten the file you know because you can actually run the hash on the content.
you can verify the file you got back is the one that you requested. so it's a really powerful primitive.
so you kind of like build up with these types of primitives of like immutable data you know content addressed storage.
and then if you want to put these kind of like mutable handles on those things then you can right.
you can say my website is at this url and it points to this ipfs hash.
and that gives me like a stable url that i can use.
but you know i have like the full history of the change of that website over time.
where i can see like the change list of the ipfs hashes.
and so if i want i can reference a specific version by its content hash.
or it's my choice whether i want to assume a little bit more like risk that the thing kind of changes.
but i prefer to point to the mutable kind of uri. so that's the general principle.
this is very interesting, so the thing that i want to ask next is on what about the case where.
um do you have like a bug in a smart contract or a query.
and that leads to some incorrect payments or or maybe funds are stolen.
i don't know if when you have that kind of a scenario what will happen with the graph, how does that handle?
well i guess there's maybe two different components to that.
you know one bugs and smart contracts you know they can certainly happen.
and i think i mean that is one area where especially as this technology is you know fairly new.
you know bugs do happen, and so you know this technology is still you know a little bit risky.
and people you know just have to be aware of the risks.
there are kind of you know different layers of solutions to these things.
you've got everything from like insurance protocols where if you've got insurance and then there's a bug then you can get a payout to cover you know your losses.
or you know there's like dispute resolution kind of protocols.
so somebody could lodge a dispute it goes to some kind of like a court system where people can adjudicate.
or like oh you know this person should get you know this amount of funds back from a pool.
so you know there's all of these kinds of like primitives that you can build up around these you know more underlying kind of immutable building blocks.
and so there's a bunch of exploration there.
and yeah as far as data kind of through the graph i mean we really kind of depend on the crypto economics of the system.
so if you have for example a gateway that is your access point to the decentralized network.
you know that gateway can you know issue a query against multiple different indexers.
it can you know compare the responses it can submit a dispute for you on chain.
all you know before you've been sending the the response back.
and so there are ways to you know the querying part itself can be made you know very secure.
you know because as i mentioned the indexers have a lot of stake you know it's kind of securing the network.
so yeah you know you just you know with these decentralized network security is obviously a really core part of you know the protocol's responsibility.
each of these protocols has to kind of design its own kind of you know security.
and and have like a security model and these things just kind of get built up from there.
so everything is it's on the responsibility of that particular graph node or sub node to also describe how it wants to handle such situations is what i'm hearing?
i wouldn't say it like that, i mean the securities is enforced by the protocol.
so there's you know rules at the protocol layer for you know how these disputes happen and how to adjudicate the disputes.
so the the securities enforced by the protocol.
okay okay gotcha.
okay i'd like to now talk a little bit about the adoption of the graph.
so i was uh you know reading some impressive numbers, i think it in december 2020 you had something like 10 billion queries.
so could you shed some light and what are the numbers you're seeing and what's the adoption rate?
yeah i mean the hosted service you know has been growing just at a pretty crazy rate.
i mean i think we're seeing a lot of growth across the entire ecosystem you know in both d5 and web3.
and the graph is this horizontal layer you know that's you know used across the entire ecosystem kind of regardless of application.
and so you know we saw traffic on the hosted service grow 100x i believe yeah over last year.
and so you know we the graph is used by you know pretty good majority of the projects building in the ethereum ecosystem.
that's where you know we've been really focused you know so far.
and we've recently announced plans to uh you know expand to other blockchains.
so this year you know big focus is on you know indexing all of the data across all these different blockchains in storage networks.
and then you know from there you know really expanding out.
because you know at this point in time you know crypto is it's well on its way to going mainstream.
and so i think there are a lot of developers out there that you know have been working at the same kinds of jobs.
doing the same thing you know for the last like five ten years.
at a certain point you get bored you know you need some purpose in your life.
a lot of those folks are now discovering crypto.
and so i think that's where a lot of the the fun is going to come from.
you know as we see more and more protocols and dapps that are tackling you know large markets.
markets that really affect a large number of people and we start to see this technology you know becoming really transformational.
so i think you've sort of answered to me what's the future of the graph and how you see things progressing.
so i anything more you'd like to add on the future?
i think it's uh you know first of all you know a lot of like the deep kind of like research and engineering problems.
have been you know solved in the space over the last few years.
and now you know we're really seeing you know this stuff you know really getting to a certain level of scale that's you know really quite exciting.
um so like one area that i think is just fascinating is decentralized governance.
and so you have these protocols some of which have you know a billion dollars plus under management.
that's controlled by the protocols you know protocols like uniswap and compound and you know even the graph.
and so once you have this type of capital controlled by a protocol then you know uh interesting next question is how do we distribute these resources.
and protocols have to make all kinds of decisions you know smart contract upgrades.
you know if they if we need to change the rules of the protocol and you know how to distribute resources from these treasuries.
and i think that's an area where you know we're seeing a lot of innovation.
because you know it's a real you know thing facing these protocols.
and you know you can see this kind of thing really growing out to more and more use cases.
you know if we have protocols and you know all these different sectors of the economy.
you know what is a protocol it's basically an internet native institution right.
it's a thing that's bigger than a corporation right.
it's the next evolution of human organization after corporations.
where you know corporations are owned and controlled by a set of shareholders that may or may not be the same as the you know participants.
and it they're closed they tend to be you know built around like you know proprietary kind of solutions.
and there's very much like you know inside the corporation and outside the corporation.
and they're trusted it's a trust boundary.
whereas with protocols there are new ways of organizing people where you know there is no such boundary.
anybody can participate in these protocols they're open.
and so they can scale to much larger numbers of people.
you know and so seeing how you know these protocols themselves evolve to be able to do more and more complex things.
be able to like distribute resources in an effective way to make high quality decisions.
i think you know that's that's one of the most fascinating things happening right now.
you know people want to dive in to see what these existing protocols are already doing.
it's already very interesting and uh it's definitely an area i would keep an eye on.
so i think this probably the last but one question that i want to ask you.
i started off with asking a very generic question, and i'm going to end with asking you again a very generic question.
so any thoughts on this you know quantum computing and how it affects the strength of the cryptographic algorithms used in blockchain infrastructure?
sure yeah, we still have some time i think before quantum computers kind of crack the existing you know hashing functions.
and it certainly this has been an area of research for you know a lot of smart cryptographers.
and i think at this point there's a pretty well understood you know set of quantum resistant you know hashing functions and cryptographic primitives.
and so they're not being widely deployed yet.
but i think they're the types of things where it's a good thing that you know these protocols are upgradable.
and so you know as those primitives get more performant and you know we kind of get closer.
you know i think it's just going to be one of these things that these protocols can coordinate on to kind of upgrade to these quantum resistant crypto primitives.
okay that's great, so i just like to end by asking where can listeners reach you if they wanted to.
would it be twitter, could you spell it out for us for our listeners?
yeah absolutely, so the graph is at graph protocol on twitter.
the initial theme that built the graph is at edgeandnode on twitter.
i'm at yanivgraph on twitter.
you can check us out at thegraph.com.
and we've got a very active discord community that you can join if you've got any questions, people are super helpful there.
we also now have a governance forum at forum.thegraph.com.
where we initially propose you know any things that are you know happening in the protocol.
usually they start out as uh forum discussions there uh first.
okay i'll make sure i put a lot of that in our show notes for listeners to see.
so thank you so much for being on the show jana, it's been great for me.
i think i've learned a lot in the 15 minutes i've spent with you, so much appreciated. yeah thanks priyanka, this was a lot of fun.
this is priyanka raghun for software engineering radio. and thanks for listening.
for listening to sc radio an educational program brought to you by ieee software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at se radio.net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on linkedin facebook twitter or through our slack channel at scradio.slack.com.
you can also email us at team sc-radio.net.
this and all other episodes of sc radio is licensed under creative commons license 2.5.
thanks for listening.